To start our discussion on protocols and services, we are going to look at two models for how data gets from a source to a destination.
The first model is the Open Systems Interconnection model, better known as the OSI model.
The OSI model is a seven-layer model that defines how data gets from what we see down to binary 1s and 0s as it travels from a source to a destination.
From the top to the bottom of the OSI model, the seven layers are as follows, with our example being data coming from a website.
On top we have the Application layer, where application services are represented, like HTTP.
Then the Presentation layer, where data is formatted and, when necessary, encrypted, like for HTML for webpages.
The Session layer opens a communication line between the source and the destination.
The Transport layer gets the data into segments and is responsible for some of the error-checking. TCP is a protocol used heavily on the Transport layer.
The Network layer is responsible for addressing data, as in giving it an IP address.
The Data-link layer is responsible for getting data into frames and is responsible for hardware addressing, such as in assigning a MAC address to the data.
And the Physical layer is responsible for the transport medium, such as Ethernet cables.
A good way to remember the OSI model is through taking the first letters of each layer and forming a sentence,
such as All People Seem To Need Data Processing, or, from the bottom up, Please Do Not Throw Sausage Pizza Away.